前情提要
Previously on The Tudors…
此刻我们齐聚一堂 参加亨利八世
We are come here together to join Henry VIII.
与简·西摩女士的神圣婚礼
and the Lady Jane Seymour.
我觉得她会令他快乐
I think she'll make him happy.
感谢上帝 那是我们大家的福音
With God's help, we'll all be happy now.
我向您保证
I promise you.
我将继续关怀玛丽女士
that I will continue to show favour to the Lady Mary.
玛丽·都铎小姐驾到
The Lady Mary Tudor.
允许我为您介绍简王后
May I present you to Her Majesty, Queen Jane.
- 伊丽莎白公主 - 全家团圆
- Princess Elizabeth. - Je suis en famille!
若新王后如传闻所说
If the new queen favours the Catholic religion.
亲睐天主教会
as she's rumoured to do,
那我们的宗教改革则岌岌可危
then our whole Reformation is surely in jeopardy.
我们必须抓紧时间解散那些修道院
We must press ahead with the dissolution of the monasteries.
有要事禀报 北部多数地区
My Lord, we have come here to tell you that a great part of the North.
突然起义征讨陛下
have risen in sudden rebellion against His Majesty.
血战到底 视死如归
We will fight, and we will die!
这些卑鄙小人叛乱危及我的国家
These wretched men have threatened my whole realm with uproar!
你告诉我反对者甚少
You told me there was little opposition.
你说多数民众乐意看到这些地方解散
You told me that most people were glad to see such places dissolved.
你大错特错了
You were wrong.
我要好好教训这些忘恩负义的判徒
I'll teach these bastard ingrates.
用一场大屠杀给他们好好上一课
a fearful bloody lesson in slaughter!
罗彻福德女士 我想任命你为
Lady Rochford, I'd like to appoint you.
我的首席侍女
my principal lady in waiting.
王后陛下
Madam, the King has.
国王已经把米索登女士收作情妇了
taken Lady Misseldon as a mistress.
别为我烦恼 我有个大好的理由足以幸福了
Do not be troubled for me for I have great reason to be happy.
- 我想你是怀孕了 - 是的
- I think you're with child. - I am.
我要您去筹备我儿降生的庆祝会
I want you to organize the celebrations for the birth of my son.
庆祝会要无比壮观
I want them to be truly spectacular.
- 王后 - 是时候了吗
- Madam! - Is it time?
是的 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
求您了 夫人 别放弃啊
Please, my Lady, don't give up!
陛下您得尽快决定
Your Majesty may have to decide soon.
是保母亲 还是保孩子
between the life of the mother or of the child.
王后陛下产下了一名健康的男孩
Her Majesty is delivered of a healthy son.
- 我有儿子了 - 至高无上
- I have a son. - Right high,
超凡卓越 高尚尊贵的爱德华王子
right excellent and noble Prince Edward.
王后的病情在急速恶化
The Queen's health has rapidly deteriorated.
我们已经竭尽所能
We have tried everything we know.
王后仍然越来越虚弱
but Her Majesty continues to weaken.
祈求上帝 别把她从我身边带走
Please, God, don't take her away from me.
我想知道陛下您
I wonder if Your Majesty.
是否愿意重结姻缘
could frame your mind towards a new marriage.
敌船来了
Enemy ships!
看在上帝的份上 快点燃烽火
For Lord's sake, light the beacon.
陛下您正四面楚歌
Your Majesty is beset by enemies.
而同克里维斯的安联姻 能与新教国结成联盟
Marriage to Anne of Cleves would bring with it.
得到军事上的大力支持
the military support of the Protestant League.
又一次成为法王与贵主陛下博弈的一颗棋子
Am I to be relieved that once more I've been used as a pawn.
我该为此欣慰吗
in a game between your master and the French King?
朕受够了 查普维斯先生
I've had enough, Mr… Chapuys.
请允许我介绍这位 托马斯·西摩先生
Allow me to present my companion, Mr. Thomas Seymour,
- 英格兰王后的兄弟 - 您好
- brother of the Queen of England. - Monsieur.
看来我们四面楚歌了 弗朗西斯阁下
Seems we are threatened from everywhere, Sir Francis.
准备好行动
Sharpen your knives.
你都都不知道我是谁吧
You don't even know who I am, do you?
你是爱德华·西摩的老婆
You're Edward Seymour's wife.
我要感谢你 弗朗西斯阁下
I thank you, Sir Francis,
以后别再碰我老婆了
in future to leave my wife alone.
我已警告过弗朗西斯·布莱恩
I've warned Sir Francis Bryan.
让他离你远点
to stay away from you.
真遗憾 他让我很开心
Well, it's a pity. He makes me laugh.
荷尔拜因先生送来了克里维斯的安的画像
Mr… Holbein has sent this portrait of Anne of Cleves.
她挺讨人喜欢
She is pleasing.
约翰阁下向我隆重介绍她
Sir John has written to me in great praise.
我要占有的这个女人 却从未能得一见
I want to possess this woman and I haven't even seen her.
这场婚姻事关重大 对吧
A great many things hang upon this marriage, do they not?
若有任何差错 将太遗憾了
What a pity if all should go awry.
克里维斯的安的事 我被欺骗了
I've been deceived about Anne of Cleves.
她本人和你们说的简直天壤之别
She is nothing like what was reported to me!
她长得简直像匹马
She looks like a horse!
大人 要不是为了平息内忧外患
My Lord, if it were not to satisfy the world and my realm,
我绝不会被逼到如此地步
I would not do what I must do this day for no earthly thing.
看来克伦威尔大人做得太过分了
It seems to me that Lord Cromwell has overreached himself.
- 我找到能取悦圣上的人了 - 她是谁
- I have found someone to amuse the King. - Who is she?
她叫凯瑟琳·霍华德
Her name is Miss Katherine Howard.
- 你芳龄几许 凯瑟琳 - 年芳十七
- How old are you, Katherine? - Seventeen.
我被送到公爵遗孀那生活
I was sent to live in the household of the Dowager Duchess.
我们玩得很疯呢
We ran a little wild.
大人 你觉得如何
What do you think, Your Grace?
我觉得很适合国王
I think she looks fit for a King.
克伦威尔大人 您因叛国罪被捕
My Lord Cromwell, you are arrested for treason.
卖国贼 卖国贼 卖国贼…
Traitor! Traitor! Traitor! Traitor! Traitor!
我才不是卖国贼
I am no traitor!
作为教会首脑 您应该找到证据
As head of Church, you should find proof.
证明这桩婚事根本没生效
that the marriage was never consummated.
派代表去见克伦威尔先生
Send a deputation to Mr. Cromwell.
让他证明支持我取消婚约
Demand of him written evidence supporting my annulment.
克伦威尔将无地自容
Cromwell will be humiliated.
他的野心害死了多少人
He was so ambitious for others' blood.
国王陛下
Your Majesty…
在下不得不向皇帝禀报
I must report to the Emperor that it has not rained.
逾时两月 此地滴雨未降
in over two months.
此等炎热酷暑实乃史无前例
Some say it is the hottest summer in living memory,
如此一来 便令五百名
which is a great inconvenience to the 500 citizens.
被监禁的异教徒倍感煎熬
the King has incarcerated on charges of heresy.
国王陛下依旧刚愎自用
His Majesty continues to demonstrate his perversity,
他时不时地会同时处死
sometimes executing both Lutherans.
路德教徒和天主教徒
and Catholics on the same day.
但一切都无法阻止国王追逐美色
But nothing deters the King from his amorous pursuits.
据我所知 他已与情妇
I am told he is already secretly married.
凯瑟琳·霍华德秘密完婚
to Mistress Katherine Howard and intends.
并拟于明日昭告天下
to show her to the world tomorrow.
- 卡尔佩珀先生 - 陛下
- Mr. Culpepper. - Majesty.
- 罗彻福德女士 - 陛下
- Lady Rochford. - Majesty.
凯瑟琳
Katherine.
您不来就寝吗
Will you not come to bed,
陛下
My Lord?
国王驾到
The King!
- 夫人 - 陛下
- My Lady. - Your Majesty.
正和查普维斯交谈的是何人
Who is that talking to Chapuys?
诺福克的长子 萨里伯爵
Norfolk's eldest son, the Earl of Surrey.
伯爵离开已有几年之久
The Earl's been away a few years,
一直在法兰西培养他的骑士精神
practicing his chivalry in France.
据说他吟诗作对 颇为放荡
They say he writes poetry and runs a little wild.
大人
Your Grace.
阁下
Excellency.
大人似乎有些心不在焉
Your Grace seems somewhat distracted.
逝者已矣 念意尚息
I was just thinking of those who are no longer here to sup with us.
即使面对吾敌 我也依然念旧
I had a moment of nostalgia, even for my enemies.
我得知托马斯·博林于近日去世
I understand Thomas Boleyn died recently.
是的 他的葬礼无人问津
Yes, and the only mourners at his funeral.
唯有子女的亡魂哀悼哭泣
were the ghosts of his children.
大人 这位是查普维斯大使
Your Grace, Ambassador Chapuys.
马里亚克先生 很高兴您带来了
Monsieur Marillac, we are happy accept your credentials.
法兰西国王的文书 欢迎来我宫中一聚
from King Francis. Welcome to our Court.
今日 我要向您引见我的新妻
I come here this day to introduce to you my new wife,
凯瑟琳王后的倾城美貌
Queen Katherine. I was first attracted to her.
令我一见倾心
by a notable appearance of honour,
还有她的蕙质兰心和似水柔情
cleanness, and maidenly behaviour…
坐拥如此尤物令我受宠若惊
It seems incredible to have obtained such a perfect jewel of womanhood.
她赐予了我如此美妙的爱情
who bears towards me such perfect love.
不只带来我梦寐以求的安宁
A love that will not only bring me the peace and tranquility I desire,
还如同重获新生
but may also bring forth.
憧憬那美好婚姻的结晶
the desired fruits of such a marriage.
- 致凯瑟琳王后 - 凯瑟琳王后千岁
- To Queen Katherine. - Queen Katherine!
现在 大家开怀畅饮吧 我饿了
Now, let's eat! I'm starving!
陛下 请允许我向您引见萨里伯爵
Your Majesty, may I introduce the Earl of Surrey.
欢迎您回到宫廷
We are very glad to welcome you back at court,
- 大人 - 陛下
- My Lord Surrey. - Majesty.
请允许我向您介绍我的新妻
Allow me to introduce my new wife.
当然 也是我的侄女
And my niece, I believe.
大人
My Lord.
抱歉
Sorry.
陛下
Majesty.
如此说来 您就是法兰西的新任使臣了
So, you are the new French ambassador.
马里亚克先生 在得知我王抛弃了
Tell me, Monsieur Marillac: what did your King really say.
他的上一任王后 您的国王有何反应
when you told him His Majesty had got rid of his last Queen?
他并未多言
Well, he didn't say much.
他只是深叹了口气 又感慨了一下
He just sighed very deeply and then he said: "Ah!"
想跳舞吗
Would you like to dance?
去吧
Go on.
等等 查尔斯
Wait. Charles.
精彩
Bravo!
马里亚克先生
Monsieur Marillac.
陛下
Majesty.
告诉法兰西国王 听闻他长子
Tell your master I was very sad to hear about the death.
太子殿下的死讯 我深感遗憾
of the Dauphin, his eldest son.
陛下
Majesty.
国王想向您提亲
His Majesty would like to propose a marriage.
让他的次子 奥尔良公爵亨利
between his second son, Henri, Duke of Orleans,
与您的爱女 玛丽小姐成婚
and your daughter, the Lady Mary.
怎么又来了
How often it comes around.
您说什么
Pardon?
抱歉
Forgive me.
你对一切尚不知情
You're new to all of this.
你可知她芳龄几何
Do you know how old she is?
年方十七
Seventeen.
我俩的婚事 你可曾告知法王
Have you told your master about her?
他作何反应
What does he say?
他定是认为我疯了吧
I suppose he thinks I'm mad.
亦或只是妒火中烧
Or else he's just plain jealous.
过来 女士们
Come here, ladies!
来看看这个
Come and look at this!
国王今早赐我的
The King sent it to me this morning.
现在 女士们
Now, ladies…
你们要发誓 从今以后 谨守承诺
You must promise that from now on, as you are all sworn in,
全部穿戴法式服饰 就如我一样
you will all dress in the French fashion, like me.
你们能保证吗
Do you promise?
遵命 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty!
我们乐意至极 陛下
We are more than happy to oblige, Your Majesty.
罗彻福德夫人
Lady Rochford.
陛下 您有一封信刚刚送到
My Lady. You have a letter, just delivered.
所为何事
What is it?
没什么 只是位旧友 琼·布尔默
Oh, nothing. Just an old friend, Joan Bulmer.
听闻我现在鸿运当头
She says that she has heard of my "Great destiny"
望我能派人接她入宫
and will I please now send for her to court.
近日遭遇某些变故
She says that some altered circumstances.
令她「痛不欲生」
have brought her "To the utmost misery in the world.
「只能终日顾影自怜」
and a most wretched life."
您会如她所愿吗
Shall you send for her?
我自会考虑 罗彻福德夫人
I shall think on it, Lady Rochford.
现在 女士们 来试试你们的新装吧
Now, ladies, why don't we try on your new dresses!
是 陛下
Yes, madam!
再给你讲个法国趣事吧
I'll tell you another amusing thing about the French.
巴黎人为庆祝冬至
To celebrate the winter solstice in Paris,
会燃起篝火 放上木桶 车轮 花环和篮子
they build a bonfire and on the top of it they put a barrel,
篮子里塞了两打活猫和一只狐狸
a wheel, garlands, and a basket filled with two dozen cats.
就这样活活烧死只为取悦国王
and a fox to be burned alive for the King's pleasure!
我还真见过弗朗西斯国王
I actually saw King Francis himself.
亲自用红色天鹅绒包裹的火炬点火
light it with a torch wrapped in red velvet.
当然
Of course!
萨里伯爵 时过境迁
Tell me, my Lord Surrey, after so long away,
您对英国朝廷有何看法
how do you find the English court?
奸佞遍布朝野
I find it full of mean creatures.
其中有不少人在为陛下效力
Many of them in the service of His Majesty.
- 伯爵所指为何人 - 那些出身卑贱的人
- Of whom do you speak? - Those men of vile birth:
律师 大学生 玩弄权术的小人
Lawyers, university men, Machiavellian intriguers.
他们别无它求
whose only desire is the destruction.
只欲毁掉这个高尚的国家
of the nobility of this country.
这些人皆令我憎恶
And I hate them all.
您是指西摩之流吗
You mean men like the Seymours?
简·西摩为国王诞下了继承人
One cannot forget their sister provided the King.
人们自然对其家族感恩戴德
with an heir to the throne.
既然您已回归 欲施何种抱负
And now that you've returned, what are your ambitions?
超越祖辈父辈的成就
To surpass the achievements of my father and my grandfather.
伯爵大人 果真志向高远
That is a very high ambition, my Lord.
吾乃霍华德家族 理应功成名就
I'm a Howard. It is expected of me.
向来如此
And always has been.
我定会成功
And I will not fail.
- 有鹿吗 - 没有
- Any deer? - No deer!
陛下 除了几只兔子和一头鹿 您今日一无所获
Majesty, you've caught nothing all day, beyond some rabbits.
为何仍笑容不减
and a deer, but you're still smiling.
诸事顺遂 自然喜由心生
Have I not every reason to be happy?
你也见过王后
You have seen the Queen.
得妻如此 夫复何求
Shouldn't the man that woman gives herself to always be happy?
回陛下 如此和乐非常
I'd say he'd be beyond happiness, Majesty.
甚是极致享受
In a higher state altogether.
查尔斯 我感觉自己已脱胎换骨
I feel almost like a new man, Charles.
不似从前那般每日为琐事烦忧
I am no longer vexed by the things that before vexed me daily.
连我的腿业已慢慢痊愈
And even my leg is beginning to heal.
性爱的确是疗伤圣药
Sex is a great medicine.
确实 您很幸运
Indeed. You are very fortunate.
你的凯瑟琳如何
How is your Catherine?
安好
She is well.
却对我情意不在
Although she no longer loves me as she once did.
- 我们分开已有时日 - 找个情妇吧
- We live mostly apart. - Take a mistress.
如有可能 我情愿令她回心转意
I would rather make her love me again, if I could.
我计划尽快带王后出巡
I want to take the Queen on a visit soon.
希望人们能和我一样爱她
I want the people to see her as I see her.
- 陛下 - 还有她的族人 萨里伯爵
- Majesty. - And her kinsman, Lord Surrey.
我要封他为侍酒官
I want to make him a cupbearer,
赐予他尊荣的象征
and give him other tokens of our esteem.
他一定会感激不尽
I am sure His Lordship will be most grateful.
你错了 大人 他只会当是理所当然
No, my Lord. He will merely see it as his birthright!
卡尔佩珀 上啊
Master Culpepper! Come on, boy!
我们再打点野味
Have them flush us out something edible!
是 陛下 助猎手出动
Yes, Majesty. Beaters!
陛下 玛丽公主求见
Majesty. The Lady Mary.
玛丽公主
Lady Mary.
夫人
Madam.
见到你令我兴奋不已
It gives me such pleasure to meet you.
陛下常说起你 不 是一刻不曾忘
The King talks about you often. No, all the time.
句句饱含热爱之情
With such affection…
我真切希望你我能相处融洽
It is my dearest wish that you and I may be kind and loving…
母慈女孝
and warm to each other…
玛丽公主 毕竟你现在是我的继女
After all, Lady Mary, you are now my stepdaughter.
无论何时您决定召见
I shall attend upon Your Majesty.
我都会伴其左右
whenever Your Majesty chooses to invite me.
谢谢你
Thank you.
小坐一下吧 我的侍女做了蛋糕
Will you stay a while? My maids have made some cakes.
不了 多谢
No, thank you.
祝您好运
I bid you a good day.
夫人
Madam.
您的旧友 琼·布尔默小姐到了
Your old friend is here: Miss Joan Bulmer.
凯瑟琳
Katherine!
难以置信 摇身一变
Are you not the luckiest,
你已成为世上最幸运和富有的女人
most fortunate woman in all the world?
- 琼 我 - 你见到我不开心吗
- Joan, I… - Are you not pleased to see me?
怎么会呢
Of course I'm pleased.
我们以前如此亲密 还记得吗
We used to be so close, didn't we?
你知道 我一直对你真心实意
You know the unfeigned love my heart has always borne towards you.
你会给我安排差事的吧
You are going to give me a position, I presume?
我会 但你要理解
I may. But you must understand…
否则我就只得深陷痛苦
Otherwise I must persist in my wretchedness.
无法脱离苦海
In my misery.
你不会抛下我吧
Say you will not turn me away.
你还记得从前常来的那个人吗
Do you remember when you-know-who used to come in,
在夜阑人静之时 潜入香闺
late at night… and slip into bed?
看在上帝份上 当心祸从口出
For God's sake, be careful what you say.
那就把我留下 你会的 对吗
But you will make me one of your ladies, won't you?
亲爱的凯瑟琳
Sweet Katherine?
大人们 法国边境的动乱
My Lords, there are new reports.
又有最新消息 请坐
of disturbances in France. Sit.
驻守阿德尔的法军守军
There is a quarrel between the French garrison at Ardres.
与我方圭尼斯的军队起了冲突
and our own at Guisnes.
法军在阿德尔建立城堡
The French built a castle at Ardres.
又建起通往加来的桥
and then a bridge into the Pale of Calais.
我军将桥砍断 不料法军竟随即重建
When our soldiers pulled it down, the French.
现在我要让法国明白
promptly rebuilt it. Now, I mean to show these French.
胆敢恣意挑衅 我定以战争还击
that I will not shy away from battle if I am provoked!
为表此意 我将派汤姆·西摩
For reasons which I am sending.
和萨里伯爵前往加来
Tom Seymour and the Earl of Surrey to Calais.
两位将前往驻军地
They will bring with them from the garrison,
军队与大炮随行
men and ordnance and they.
在阿德尔摆开阵营
will make a show of force before Ardres.
如此情形下 法国要么乖乖求饶
In which case the French must either decide to desist…
要么等着开战
or fight.
遵旨
Aye.
- 玫瑰花雨 - 王后陛下
- It's raining roses! - My Lady.
托马斯·卡尔佩珀先生求见
Mr. Thomas Culpepper is here.
卡尔佩珀先生
Mr. Culpepper.
陛下 国王陛下谴我来此
Your Majesty. The King has sent me.
这边请
Come.
卡尔佩珀先生
Mr. Culpepper?
陛下谴小人前来宣旨
His Majesty wants you to know that you will shortly.
近期您将陪同陛下出巡威廉姆·佩吉特爵士
accompany him on a visit to Sir William Paget's estates.
位于伯克郡的领地 望此行令您愉快
in Berkshire for your pastime and disport.
蒙陛下厚爱
I am very grateful to His Majesty.
我对此行非常期待
and I look forward to the visit very much.
陛下还颁旨
His Majesty also wants you to know that he has settled.
将贝纳德堡赐予您
Baynard's Castle on you as your jointure.
贝纳德堡在哪里
Where is Baynard's Castle?
位于伦敦 泰晤士河北岸
It is here in London, on the north bank of the Thames,
弗利特河塔附近 您在河边就可以看到
near the Fleet Tower. You've probably seen it from the river.
很大吗
Is it that big one?
是的 非常宏伟
Yes. It's a very big one.
这样啊…
In that case…
请回禀陛下 我非常非常感谢他
please tell His Majesty that I am very, very grateful to him.
我不敢相信自己拥有了一座城堡
I cannot imagine owning a castle.
陛下
Majesty.
陛下对法之举实乃果断英明
May I commend your Majesty on taking decisive action.
感谢陛下委以重任于舍弟
against the French and for honouring my brother with a command.
陛下也希望您接受此礼物
His Majesty also desires you to accept this gift.
请回禀陛下
Please tell His Majesty that…
您非常非常非常感谢他
That you're very, very, very grateful.
是的
Yes.
卡尔佩珀先生 有些话不知当向谁讲
I do not know who to say this to, Mr.Culpepper.
但 当我出宫
But, when I go about,
陪国王陛下出巡时
and when I shall go with the King on a visit,
我
I am…
不习惯众人注视的目光
not so used to everyone looking at me.
有时 甚至希望大家不要看着我
And sometimes wish they would not do.
王后 绅士们望您一眼
My Lady, you must give men leave to look,
便会敬您为天人
for they will look upon you.
由心而生 情不自禁
There is no help for it.
告退 陛下
Your Majesty.
罗彻福德女士
Lady Rochford.
陛下
Your Majesty.
你好 夫人
Hello, my Lady.
我爱你 吻我吧
I love you. Kiss me.
不嘛
No!
请吻我吧
Please kiss me.
那好吧
Well, all right then.
来吧
Come here.
我的爱 我的王后
Oh, oh, my Lady! Oh, my Queen!
我的陛下
Oh, Your Majesty!
我会离宫一段时间
I'm going away for a while.
莱斯利先生会告知你行程
Mr. Risley will supply you with an itinerary.
遵命 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
我离开后要举行一次议会
Also while I'm away I intend to call a meeting of the Council.
所有议员必须到会
Every councillor must attend.
不容任何借口缺席
or give very good reason why he may not.
- 遵命陛下 - 照此去办
- Majesty. - That's the agenda.
还有 我希望在离宫期间
Also, while we're away I intend for work to begin.
进行王宫修缮工作
on the improvements to the palace.
沿东河 新建一处
There will be a new front along the east river,
玛丽公主的御用寝室
privy lodgings for the Lady Mary,
还有宴厅
and a banqueting house.
该死的热
Damn this heat…
请重述 陛下
Pardon, Your Majesty?
大人 近来有哪些人被囚于伦敦塔
Tell me, My Lord, who is presently kept in the Tower?
格雷大人 在爱尔兰通奸而被起诉
There is Lord Grey, accused of grave misconduct in Ireland;
莱尔大人 在加来犯同罪 还有约翰·内维尔爵士
Lord Lisle, the same but in Calais; and Sir John Neville,
陛下 您可能记得由他领导的
who led, as you may remember, Your Majesty,
近来北部的叛乱 他因叛乱罪而受审
the recent disturbance in the north, for which he has been arraigned.
另有一位出身显贵者
Theris also one other of high birth,
王后的堂兄 戴克斯大人
namely the queen's cousin, Lord Dacres.
所犯何罪
For what crime?
陛下 戴克斯大人是位23岁的年轻人
Your Majesty, Lord Dacres is a young man of 23 years,
与伙伴醉酒之后
who, along with some companions, and after a drinking bout,
殴打一位老翁致死
set upon an old man in a brawl and killed him.
他的父亲及其他家庭成员
His father and other members of his family.
曾致函陛下乞求宽恕
have written to Your Majesty begging you,
看在他年少无知 乞求您的仁慈宽恕
for the sake of his youth, to show mercy.
我离宫后 将前三位处死
The first three are to be executed whilst I'm away.
戴克斯大人另当别论
Lord Dacres is different.
他玷污了其高贵出身
He has besmirched his noble birth.
行为与贱民犯罪无异
by behaving like a common criminal.
那他就应与贱民受同刑
And so I intend he shall be treated like one.
游街至泰伯恩行刑场
Have him dragged through the streets to Tyburn.
公开处予绞刑 以儆效尤
and there hanged in public, for all to see.
遵旨 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
上帝啊 何时再天降甘霖？
For God's sakes, will it ever rain?
赫福德夫人 萨里伯爵求见
Lady Hertford, the Earl of Surrey, my Lady.
大人 敢问有何能为您效劳
My Lord. How may I be of assistance?
我本以为能在此地面见伯爵
I rather trusted to find the Earl here.
我很快将启程前往法国
I am leaving presently for France.
他是军人 我想征求些许建议
He is a military man. I wanted some advice.
我丈夫正在议会同国王会晤
My husband is in council with the King.
我的朋友曾向我说起过您
Soneone of my acquaintance has told me about you,
向我描绘了您的美德和才智
painting such a picture of your virtues and your talents.
令我不禁期待能有幸与您结识
that I thought to make myself known to you.
我新近才从法国归来
I am recently returned from France.
在宫廷中密友甚少
and I know intimately so few people at court.
先生 那现在我们就算认识了
Well, Sir, now we are introduced.
若此为您所求
If that is what you wanted?
我会转告我丈夫 您希望与他会面
I will tell my husband that you wish to speak to him.
谢谢
Thank you.
夫人
My Lady.
爱德华先生
Sir Edward!
这些鞋子务必妥善收藏精心保管
These shoes must be nicely put and always carefully attended.
是 陛下
Yes, my Lady.
陛下 国王来了
Your Majesty, the King is here!
天呐
Oh my!
亲爱的
Sweetheart,
我想为您介绍两个人
there are two people come to be introduced to you.
- 布赖恩夫人 - 是 陛下
- Lady Bryan. - Your Majesty.
这位是我的儿子 爱德华王子
This is my son, Prince Edward.
上前来 孩子
Come forward, child.
这位是我的新王后 凯瑟琳
This is my new Queen, Katherine.
- 向她问好 - 您好 陛下
- Say hello to her. - Hello, Your Majesty.
真是个可爱的孩子
Oh, he's such a sweet boy!
您好 殿下
Hello, Your Grace.
- 很高兴认识您 - 谢谢
- I am so delighted to meet you. - Thank you.
他可安好 吃得可好 酷暑有没有影响到他
Is he well? Eating well? How does the heat affect him?
即便酷热如此 也务必确保他穿着严实
Even though it is so hot he must always be wrapped up.
- 以防着凉 - 殿下安好康健
- against any sudden chills. - He is very well and healthy,
我们的服侍照顾极尽周正无缺
and every care that could be taken is taken for his better comfort.
另一方面 也不可过分宠溺他
On the other hand, don't spoil him too much!
继续
Go on.
做个乖孩子 听到了吗
And be a good boy, do you hear?
谢谢您 先生 祝您日安 夫人
Thank you, sir. Good day, Madam.
欢迎 伊丽莎白
Welcome, Elizabeth.
这位是我的女儿
This is my daughter,
伊丽莎白公主
the Lady Elizabeth.
陛下 很荣幸能认识您
Your Majesty, I am honoured to be presented to you.
祝您欢愉喜乐
and wish you every joy and happiness.
能认识您我也很荣幸 伊丽莎白小姐
It is also an honour for me to meet you, Lady Elizabeth.
您是个非常漂亮的小淑女
You are a very pretty young lady.
谢谢 夫人
Thank you, Madam.
我要送给您这个
I want to give you these.
不算昂贵 但能让您记得我
They are of not much value, but will remind you of me.
陛下真是太慷慨了
Your Majesty is very generous.
我将永远视若珍宝 陛下
I will always cherish it. Your Majesty.
继续整理 我们明日出发
Carry on packing; we depart tomorrow.
夫人
Madam.
莱斯利先生
Now, Mr. Risley.
- 死刑判决书 赫福德大人 - 大人
- The death warrants, my Lord Hertford. - My Lord.
格雷大人
Lord Grey.
莱尔大人 约翰·内维尔爵士
Lord Lisle. Sir John Neville.
还有戴克斯大人
And Lord Dacres.
真令人同情 如此年轻
I pity him for his youth.
听说法官宣判时都悲叹不已
They say the judges wept when they read his sentence.
上帝保佑 莱斯利先生 让那些悲叹的法官们省省吧
God save us, Mr. Risley, from weeping judges.
大人
My Lord.
萨里伯爵启程前来见过你吗
Did Surrey speak to you before he left?
没有 自他回到宫廷
No. Since his return.
这位爵爷到处宣扬
the Earl has made it plain to all who will listen.
说他鄙视我们这些 「新晋份子」
that he despises us as "New men."
我看不出来他有何必要跟你打交道
I don't suppose that he would deal with you?
也许吧
Perhaps.
这有何了不得
Why is it so important?
萨里伯爵身世显赫家财万贯
Surrey is heir to a great title and a great fortune.
他的家族有皇室血统
His family have royal blood.
显然即便是你 也能看出其中的利益
Surely even you can see the merits of dealing with him.
贝克夏老城堡
威廉爵士
Sir William?
王后与我对您的盛情款待深表感谢
The Queen and I thank you for your most lavish hospitality.
陛下实在是太仁慈了
Oh, Your Majesty is most gracious.
您与王后能造访寒舍 实属莫大的荣幸
We are so honoured that you and your Queen have chosen to visit us.
理查德爵士
Sir Richard.
陛下 我刚从宫里赶来
Your Majesty. I just came from court.
收到法国来的消息
We have had news from France.
显然在我到达不久 托马斯·西摩爵士
Apparently, soon after I arrived, Sir Thomas Seymour.
和萨里伯爵 已按您吩咐 做好了战事部署
and Lord Surrey, as you commanded, made warlike preparations.
展示了我方实力
and showed their strength,
随后向法方表明了决议
and afterwards made overtures to the French governor.
双方交换了礼物
Some gifts were exchanged.
他们还邀请法国方面观赏摔跤比赛
and the French were invited to watch a wrestling match.
原本直到近日 双方剑拔弩张 一触即发
And where, until recently, nothing but war had been talked of,
而现在却对此互不提及 只望和平共处
now there is no mention but of wishing to live at peace.
这么说他们已妥善处理
Then it was all well done.
尽管如此 理查德爵士 我内心还是有些许失望
And yet, Sir Richard, something inside me is disappointed.
我渴望战争
It hungers for a war.
过去我曾深谙此种疯狂的热望
I have known its mad excitements only once,
那是很久以前了
that was a long time ago.
有意思 我真心觉得
Funny. You know, I actually thought.
法国人这次定然感恩戴德
the French might oblige me this time.
陛下
Majesty.
你快乐吗
Are you happy?
是否心满意足 万事遂愿
Do you have everything you want, everything you need?
- 告诉我 - 是的 别无他求
- Tell me. - Yes, everything.
不过还有一事
There is one thing.
何事
What is it?
只是…
It's just that…
玛丽公主待我毫无敬意
the Lady Mary doesn't treat me with respect.
她不应如此 对吗
And I think she ought to, don't you?
她会改变态度 相信我
She will. Believe me.
给她点时间
Give her time.
她尚不适应这变化
All this is new to her,
但最终会接受你
but she will grow used to you.
喜爱你
And then she will love you.
但愿如此
I hope so.
凯瑟琳
Katherine, Katherine.
我累了 真的很累
I'm tired. I'm very tired.
明日还要为国事繁忙
I have a long day tomorrow.
晚安 吾爱
Good night, sweetheart.
好梦
Sleep well.
晚安 陛下
Good night, Your Majesty.
晚安 夫人
Good night, my Lady.
琼
Joan!
- 你干嘛 - 别担心 我不会久留
- What is it? - Don't worry. I won't stay.
只想聊聊天
I just want to talk.
聊什么
About what?
我们过去常这样 还记得吗
This is how it used to be. Remember? You and me together.
我警告过你 当心祸从口出
I told you to mind what you say.
我只是跟你讲讲嘛
I'm only talking to you.
他们两个夜里就会进来
And then the two of them would come in,
双双对对 神仙眷侣
the one for you, and the other mine.
黑暗中浪声绵绵 娇喘吁吁
And all that puffing and blowing in the dark.
你们忘情亲吻
And you and him would kiss.
莺歌燕舞 如胶似漆
and hang by your bellies like two sparrows.
这没什么
There was no harm in it.
我们都想着以后会结为夫妻
We were agreed we were to be married.
这事你告诉国王了吗
Is that what you told the King?
别傻了
Don't be stupid.
过去的事
I don't need to tell him anything about…
何必再提
what happened before.
若你胆敢走漏风声 我发誓将…
And if you talk of it to anyone I swear I'll…
嘘 我还指望
Hush. Hush. Do you suppose.
留在宫廷 享受荣华富贵呢
I don't like being at court, like a special person?
那你就以荣誉发下毒誓
Then swear on your honour, and hope to die,
绝不对任何人吐露半点
that you will speak of it to nobody,
包括我的那些女仆
not even any of my other ladies.
遵命 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
我对天发誓
I do so swear.
真心诚意
Honestly.
很好 现在回去睡觉
Good. Now go back to bed.
还记得这轻抚吗
And do you remember this?
我如今贵为王后
I am Queen now.
你要听从吩咐
Do as I command.
威廉爵士何其慷慨 敞开酒窖招待我们
How very obliging of Sir William to open his cellar for us.
我还以为是爱德华爵士你打开的呢
I rather thought, Sir Edward, that it was you who opened it.
我刚才饥渴难耐
Well, I was thirsty!
此时仍未满足
I still am!
- 天啊 她还真是放荡 - 说谁呢
- By God she's wanton. - Who is?
你很清楚我在说谁
You know very well who I mean.
凯瑟琳王后 她就是只小野猫
Queen Katherine. She's a little fireball.
让你欲火焚身 卡尔佩珀先生
Too hot for you, Mr. Culpepper.
是吗
Really?
啊哈
Uh-huh.
你就没有想过她一丝不挂的模样
Tell me you can't imagine her without her clothes on.
玉体裸呈 春光无限
Just picture her naked body.
双峰诱人
Those breasts.
美腿丰腴 粉臀娇翘
Those thighs. That sweet plump little arse.
神啊
Holy Jesus.
这些全属国王私有
All those things belong to the King.
祝各位先生晚安
I bid you gentlemen good night.
换作我
And if I were you,
就知趣地离开威廉爵士的厨房
I would not outstay your welcome in Sir William's kitchen.
喝再多酒都无法熄灭对她的欲望
I can't drink enough to banish the thoughts of her.
明日我们出去找点乐子 解解渴
Tomorrow let's go out and find something to quench that thirst.
- 好啊 - 哈哈
- Ya! - Ya!
- 留步 - 先生们 日安
- Ho there! - Sir, a good day.
日安 你是何人
And to you. And who are you?
守园人的妻子 先生
The wife of the park-keeper, sir.
- 你丈夫呢 - 他去集市了 先生
- And where is your husband? - He's away at a fair, sir.
这里可有别人 孩子呢
Anyone else here? Your children?
没有 先生
No, sir.
我曾有个女儿 但不幸夭折 先生
I had a daughter, sir, but she died.
这里没有别人
There's no one else here.
有何贵干 先生
Can I help you, sir?
你能解我燃眉之急 亦能从中取乐
You can do me a great favour, and it will please you too.
别这样 先生
Oh no, sir!
知道我是谁吗
Do you know who I am?
我身为枢密院成员 侍奉国王
A gentleman of the Privy Chamber. I serve the King.
- 走 我们进去 - 不
- Now, let's go inside. - No!
你既贵为上流君子
If, as you say, you are a gentleman,
那就不要强人所难
then you would not try to force me against my will.
我恳请你就此离开
You would just leave, as I ask you to.
- 追 - 这边
- Come on! - This way!
绕过去
Around back!
别跑啊 小母鸡
Come on, little chicken!
兄弟们 上吧
Come on, boys!
- 放过我吧 - 瞧她跑的小样
- Leave me alone! - Look at her run!
- 到时有你乐的 - 抓住她
- Hey! You'll enjoy it! - Take her!
来吧 放松点
Come on now. Easy.
按住她
Hold her still.
你是谁
Who are you, there?
我是守园人罗珀 先生
Mr. Roper, sir. The park-keeper.
罗珀先生
Mr. Roper.
找我所为何事
What on earth do you want with me?
您心知肚明 阁下
You know very well what I want, sir.
我要寻求公义 我深知你的卑劣行径
I want justice. I know what you've done.
此行前来是为将你带至执行官那里
I have come to take you to the Sheriff.
- 跟我走吧 阁下 - 休得碰我
- Come, sir. - Don't you dare touch me.
你应该了解你的长官
You should know your betters.
滚回你的狗窝去
Now go back to your pigsty.
阁下 我会走的
I will go, sir,
去寻找能为我主持公道的执行官
and fetch the Sheriff myself, whose justice is better than yours!
省去执行官的麻烦吧
I would rather not trouble the Sheriff.
使你封口 所需多少
How much do you want for your silence?
说个准数吧
Come on, man.
反正也没实际伤害
What real harm was done?
收下这枚金币 足以买十二头猪
Take a gold crown, enough to buy a dozen pigs,
对此既往不咎
and forget the whole matter.
不 阁下
No, sir.
耻辱将永留贱内
For the shame would still be there in my wife's eyes.
以及我的心中
And in my soul.
操 你个蠢货
Damn you for a fool.
蒙您之邀令我倍感惊讶
I have to say I was surprised at your invitation.
真的吗
Really?
大人 我以为您早已司空见惯
I had imagined that very little would surprise you, my Lord.
我此生阅历无数 理应习以为常
It is true that I have seen most things in my life.
可我发现人们总是惊喜不断
But I find that people can always be surprising.
我想和你交友 因而邀请你至此
I invited you here because I want us to be friends.
何种朋友
What kind of friends?
好朋友
Good friends.
无人想被诅咒
Who wants to be cursed?
有所畏惧才会有所顾忌
People are good when they are afraid.
当人们无所畏惧
When they are not afraid…
他们就会无法无天
they can be anything.
我就无所畏惧
I am not afraid.
我永远无所畏惧
I will never be afraid.
凯瑟琳·霍华德
Katherine Howard!
陛下
Your Majesty!
议员们皆已到达
My Councillors are arriving.
那我得尽快沐浴更衣
Oh, then I'd better wash.
是的
Yes.
- 先生们 议员们 - 陛下
- Gentlemen. My Lords. - Your Majesty.
今早奏本 赫福德勋爵
What is your report, my Lord Hertford?
回陛下
Your Majesty,
您离开期间 伦敦爆发了小规模瘟疫
there was a small outbreak of plague in the city during your absence,
不过谢天谢地 现已平息
which now has abated, thank God.
陛下下令建造的房屋都已动工
The building works Your Majesty requested have all commenced.
格雷勋爵 莱尔勋爵 约翰·内维尔爵士和戴克斯勋爵
And the executions of Lords Grey and Lisle, of Sir John Neville and Lord Dacres.
业已遵照陛下指令予以处决
have all been carried out in accordance with your Majesty's wishes.
坐吧
Sit.
议员们
My Lords.
至于牢中那五百名异教徒嫌疑犯
I refer to the 500 men kept in prison on suspicion of heresy.
依我之意 应全部赦免并将其释放
It is my desire that they should be pardoned and therefore released.
陛下宽宏大度 心系天下
Your Majesty shows remarkable charity.
吾理应如此
Why should I not?
吾主告诫我们
Does our Lord not commend us.
应永怀慈爱和信实
to never to let mercy and faithfulness depart from us?
王子近况如何
How is my boy?
回陛下 爱德华王子一切安好
Prince Edward is very well, Your Majesty.
弗朗西斯国王替其儿子 奥尔良公爵
King Francis has formally proposed a marriage contract.
正式向玛丽公主求婚
between his son, Henri, Duc of Orleans, and Lady Mary.
我们不应当也不能
We do not, and cannot,
轻信弗朗西斯国王
trust the intentions of King Francis.
- 他仍意图侵略我国 - 是的
- and still think he means to invade this realm. - Aye.
加来事件只是对我们的初探
Events at Calais were just a preliminary exercise to test our resolve.
因而我们仍须时刻警惕海岸防线
In which case we must continue to look to our coastal defences.
保卫帝国安全
and favour the Emperor.
下一个主题是凯瑟琳王后
Now, to the subject of Queen Katherine.
我意图将先前属于简·西摩的领地与庄园
It is my intention to settle upon her all the lands and manors.
赐予她
which formerly belonged to Jane Seymour.
以及先前属于托马斯·克伦威尔领地
Furthermore, some lands and properties formerly.
及产业也一并赐予她
in the possession of Thomas Cromwell are also to be settled upon her.
将宫中其他徽章撤下 用其徽章取而代之
Her badges and emblems are to be set up in all palaces, replacing all others,
从今往后凯瑟琳享受英格兰王后待遇
and henceforth she is in all ways to be treated as the Queen of England.
怎么了
What is it?
听
Listen.
听见没
Can you hear that?
下雨了 下雨了
It's… It's raining!
下雨了
It's raining!
凯瑟琳 你去哪
Katherine. Katherine! Where are you going?
下雨了 亨利 下雨了
It's raining! Henry! Henry, it's raining!